<!DOCTYPE html><html>
<head>
<title>The Number of Publications Used as a Metric of the NOAO WIYN Queue Experiment</title>
<!--Generated on Wed Jul  3 21:37:27 2019 by LaTeXML (version 0.8.4) http://dlmf.nist.gov/LaTeXML/.-->

<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8">
<meta name="keywords" lang="en" content="PAC codes 95.45 95.55; instrumentation: miscellaneous—methods:
miscellaneous—sociology of astronomy">
</meta>
</meta>
</head>
<body>
<div class="ltx_page_main">
<div class="ltx_page_content">
<article class="ltx_document">
<h1 class="ltx_title ltx_title_document">The Number of Publications Used as a Metric of the NOAO WIYN Queue
Experiment</h1>
<div class="ltx_authors">
<span class="ltx_creator ltx_role_author">
<span class="ltx_personname">Philip Massey, Mary Guerrieri,
and Richard R. Joyce
</span><span class="ltx_author_notes"><span>
<span class="ltx_contact ltx_role_affiliation">Kitt Peak National Observatory, National Optical Astronomy
Observatory<span id="id1" class="ltx_note ltx_role_affiliation"><sup class="ltx_note_mark">1</sup><span class="ltx_note_outer"><span class="ltx_note_content"><sup class="ltx_note_mark">1</sup><span class="ltx_note_type">affiliation: </span>Operated by AURA
under cooperative agreement with the
National Science Foundation.</span></span></span>
<br class="ltx_break">P.O. Box 26732, Tucson, AZ 85726-6732
</br>
</span></span></span></span>
</div>

<div class="ltx_abstract">
<h6 class="ltx_title ltx_title_abstract">Abstract</h6>
<p id="id2" class="ltx_p">We use the number of papers published in 1998 and 1999 to test the
hypothesis that the queue observing mode at WIYN leads to a
significantly higher scientific throughput than classical mode
observing. We use the papers published from the 4-m, and papers
published from the non-queue WIYN time as controls, requiring only that
the data be obtained after 1996 August 1, at which time the WIYN queue
was in its third full semester of operation, and the WIYN instruments
functional and stable. The number of papers published from the queue
data is actually 1.5 times smaller (on a per night basis) than from the
4-m, and roughly comparable to (but lower than) the number published
from non-queue WIYN time. Thus neither comparison offers any <span id="id2.1" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">support</span> for the hypothesis that queue leads to a higher scientific
throughput. The number of papers is relatively small, but the
statistics are sufficiently robust to <span id="id2.2" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">reject</span> the possibility that
queue observing at WIYN leads to a factor of 1.5 enhancement in
publication rate with a 99.3% confidence in comparison to the 4-m,
and with an 89.9% confidence in comparison with non-queue WIYN time.
We consider several explanations, and urge that other observatories
planning to employ the queue mode include some controls to provide
an objective evaluation of its success.</p>
</div>
<div class="ltx_keywords">PAC codes 95.45 95.55; instrumentation: miscellaneous—methods:
miscellaneous—sociology of astronomy
</div>
<section id="S1" class="ltx_section">
<h2 class="ltx_title ltx_title_section">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_section">1 </span>Introduction</h2>

<div id="S1.p1" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p1.1" class="ltx_p">The 3.5-m Wisconsin-Indiana-Yale-NOAO (WIYN) telescope was dedicated on
1994 October 15, and shared-risk observing began in 1995 March. NOAO’s share
of the time is 40%, and nearly all of this has been carried out in “queue” mode, where the observations
from highly ranked proposals are placed in a queue and executed during
nights assigned to the queue program. The observations are carried out by
highly experienced professionals, who are extremely familiar with
the instrumentation, without the direct assistance of the proposing astronomer.
A small fraction of the NOAO time
is scheduled out in “classical mode”, with the
observers present at the telescope. The time allocated to the
university consortium members (roughly 60%)
is all carried out in classical mode.</p>
</div>
<div id="S1.p2" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p2.1" class="ltx_p">The goal
of the NOAO WIYN queue experiment was
eloquently described by Silva &amp; De Young (1996) as an empirical test
of “the hypothesis that in the face of a high over-subscription rate, the
science throughput of WIYN can be maximized by executing
the most highly ranked science programs first, completing datasets in a timely
manner, allowing a larger range of program lengths, and matching the
observing program to the observing conditions on an observation-by-observation
basis.”</p>
</div>
<div id="S1.p3" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p3.1" class="ltx_p">The WIYN queue has often been described as an “experiment” at least in part
because other observatories are considering scheduling some or all of their time
in this mode, and NOAO staff have felt that what we can learn from the WIYN
queue will be useful to others.
In an era that sees both the proliferation of very large
(<math id="S1.p3.1.m1.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\geq" display="inline"><semantics id="S1.p3.1.m1.1a"><mo id="S1.p3.1.m1.1.1" xref="S1.p3.1.m1.1.1.cmml">≥</mo><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S1.p3.1.m1.1b"><geq id="S1.p3.1.m1.1.1.cmml" xref="S1.p3.1.m1.1.1"></geq></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S1.p3.1.m1.1c">RELOP:greater-than-or-equals</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S1.p3.1.m1.1d">\geq</annotation></semantics></math>8 m) telescopes, but ever-tightening financial resources, observatories
are scrambling to understand how to maximize their scientific return.</p>
</div>
<div id="S1.p4" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p4.1" class="ltx_p">Queue observing offers a variety of theoretical advantages, as nicely
summarized by Mountain (1996) and
Boroson et al. (1998). For very highly ranked programs that require
rare conditions, queue observing may be the only practical way to acquire such data. Queue observing naturally allows synoptic observations, and such
scheduling easily accommodates target-of-opportunity requests, such as optical
follow-ups of gamma-ray bursts or supernovae. Furthermore, as instrumentation
becomes more complex, queue observing carried out by dedicated observers
may result in more efficient use of telescope time than if the observations
were carried out by visitors who uses the equipment only occasionally.
This contention is partially supported by evidence that
observers collect less data on the first night of an observing run than
on subsequent nights (Bohannan 1998).</p>
</div>
<div id="S1.p5" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p5.1" class="ltx_p">However, there are obvious down-sides to the queue mode. The astronomer is not
present at the telescope, and therefore cannot make real-time decisions
concerning the data. Serendipity is eliminated, as are the risky programs
many of us have snuck in during gaps in our main observing program, and which
have sometimes led to the more interesting results.
Some of us suspect, rightly or wrongly,
that we could better carry out our own observations.
And, there is not the same strong sense of
“data ownership” that comes
with having carried out the observations ourselves: the memory of a night
may provide details that are relevant to the interpretation of the reduced
data, as well as providing an emotional impetus for seeing the project
through to its completion.</p>
</div>
<div id="S1.p6" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p6.1" class="ltx_p">There is also a non-negligible expense of
running a queue, which is off-set to some degree
by the smaller support
required for visiting astronomers.</p>
</div>
<div id="S1.p7" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p7.1" class="ltx_p">Boroson (1996) has described a simulation program that can be used to
test how successfully programs are completed in a queue mode
vs. a classical mode, using Monte Carlo sampling of characteristic
observing conditions (weather, seeing) for the site. Boroson
et al. (1998) used this simulation program comparing queue mode and classical
scheduling
for two actual semesters (1997) of WIYN programs, concluding that
queue scheduling at WIYN has led to a significant gain in efficiency
and scientific effectiveness.</p>
</div>
<div id="S1.p8" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p8.1" class="ltx_p">Now that the queue experiment has run for several years, we thought it would be worth examining the gain using some real-world measure.
As emphasized by Boroson et al. (1998), much of the argument about observing
modes can be emotional. We seek some metric that we can use to <span id="S1.p8.1.1" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">test</span>
the <span id="S1.p8.1.2" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">hypothesis</span> enunciated above that the queue observing mode leads
to significant improvement in the <span id="S1.p8.1.3" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">science throughput</span>. One such
simple metric is the number of refereed papers published. This may not be
as meaningful in its long-term impact on astronomy as, say,
the number of important new discoveries,
but at least it has the advantage of being quantifiable, and, if the
experimental and control samples are well matched, equitable and fair.</p>
</div>
<div id="S1.p9" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p9.1" class="ltx_p">We choose to compare the number of papers produced by the WIYN queue to the
following two controls,
each with its advantages and disadvantages:</p>
<ol id="S1.I1" class="ltx_enumerate">
<li id="S1.I1.i1" class="ltx_item" style="list-style-type:none;">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_item">1.</span> 
<div id="S1.I1.i1.p1" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.I1.i1.p1.1" class="ltx_p">The number of papers produced by observations made over the same time
period with the Mayall 4-m telescope.</p>
</div>
</li>
<li id="S1.I1.i2" class="ltx_item" style="list-style-type:none;">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_item">2.</span> 
<div id="S1.I1.i2.p1" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.I1.i2.p1.1" class="ltx_p">The number of papers produced by observations made over the same time
period by non-queue use of WIYN; i.e., primarily the time used by the
consortium universities.</p>
</div>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
<div id="S1.p10" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p10.1" class="ltx_p">The first comparison has the primary advantage that both the 4-m and WIYN
proposals have undergone similar scrutiny by
the same time allocation committees (TACs),
which often consider such factors as the past track-record of the proposers
as well as the
scientific excellence of the proposals. Thus proposers to the 4-m and
WIYN will feel similar pressures to publish in a timely manner, and the
feasibility of the proposals has been carefully evaluated. Users of the
university time may choose to undertake
longer-term projects, leading ultimately
to more important results, but not processing the same rapid turn around
from observing to publication.
We offer the second comparison as there may be differences in the actual
on-sky performance of the two telescopes that would affect the results:
the 4-m is a mature telescope, possibly with fewer teething problems, than
the newer WIYN.</p>
</div>
<div id="S1.p11" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S1.p11.1" class="ltx_p">If the queue leads to significantly higher
scientific throughput, then we expect that the number of papers published using
data obtained via the queue should be significantly
greater than those produced by the
control samples, after normalization on the basis of the number of scheduled
nights.</p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="S2" class="ltx_section">
<h2 class="ltx_title ltx_title_section">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_section">2 </span>The Data Set</h2>

<div id="S2.p1" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S2.p1.1" class="ltx_p">All of the 1998 and 1999 issues of the main US astronomy journals
were examined
for papers which used 4-m and/or WIYN observations. The complete list of 135
papers is given in Table A1 of the Appendix.</p>
</div>
<div id="S2.p2" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S2.p2.1" class="ltx_p">In order to make a fair
comparison, we restricted ourselves to only those papers for which the data
were obtained in semester “1996B” or later (i.e., after 1996 August 1).
This was the third full semester of WIYN queue time, and the first semester in
which both the imager and fiber positioner were fully functional.
(A non-linearity problem with the S2KB imager chip was discovered and
fixed during the 1996A semester, and a mechanical problem which compromised the
positioning accuracy of the Hydra fiber positioner was fixed in 1996 March.)</p>
</div>
<div id="S2.p3" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S2.p3.1" class="ltx_p">We list in Table 1 the number of papers published during 1998 and 1999.
Six papers used both 4-m <span id="S2.p3.1.1" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">and</span> WIYN data; we chose to count each of
these papers separately for both telescopes, depending upon the date
in which the data were obtained for the telescope under consideration; i.e.,
if the data for WIYN was obtained in 1996B or later, but the 4-m data was
obtained prior to 1996, it would count as a WIYN publication but not as a
4-m paper. There were six papers in our list in which the data
collected were such a minor component of the
paper that we chose not to count the paper at all; only one of these used
the WIYN queue, and in that case the data had been published previously by
the original proposers.
</p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="S3" class="ltx_section">
<h2 class="ltx_title ltx_title_section">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_section">3 </span>Results</h2>

<section id="S3.SS1" class="ltx_subsection">
<h3 class="ltx_title ltx_title_subsection">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_subsection">3.1 </span>Comparison of the WIYN and the 4-m</h3>

<div id="S3.SS1.p1" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S3.SS1.p1.1" class="ltx_p">In order to make a valid comparison, we must first take into account that not
as much time is scheduled for the WIYN queue as for the 4-m. We expect the
answer is about 40%, as NOAO receives
40% of the time on WIYN, and almost
all of this goes to the queue. However, the 4-m is shut down during July
and August, while WIYN continues to operate; on the other hand, there
are more engineering nights scheduled at WIYN. One could use the
total number of clear hours spent observing as
the normalization, but these data are hard to extract reliably. Instead, we
took the final observing schedules for semesters 1996B, 1997A, 1997B, 1998A, and
1998B, and simply counted the number of nights assigned to the WIYN queue,
and to science operations at the 4-m. (For the latter, we included half-night
instrument “checkout” nights, as much of this time is typically
returned to the observers
scheduled on the second half; full-night “check” nights and engineering
nights were excluded. We excluded all engineering nights scheduled at WIYN,
although occasionally queue observations are obtained during such time.)
The numbers of nights so scheduled for the WIYN
queue and for the 4-m are 260 and 656 respectively; i.e.,
the number of nights scheduled to the WIYN queue turned out to be 39.6% of the
nights scheduled at the 4-m.</p>
</div>
<div id="S3.SS1.p2" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S3.SS1.p2.1" class="ltx_p">If the hypothesis described above is
correct, we would expect the number of publications based upon WIYN queue data
to be significantly greater than 40% of those produced by the 4-m.
Instead, we find in Table 1 that there
were only 9 papers produced by WIYN queue data as opposed to 34 papers
produced by the 4-m; i.e., 26%. Thus there are actually
1.5 times fewer papers published (on a per night basis) based on
queue WIYN data relative to those based on 4-m data. This comparison does not
support the hypothesis of greater science throughput by the WIYN queue.</p>
</div>
<div id="S3.SS1.p3" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S3.SS1.p3.1" class="ltx_p">Can we rule out the hypothesis given the small number statistics? If we assume
the simplest model that a 1<math id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m1.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\sigma" display="inline"><semantics id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m1.1a"><mi id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m1.1.1" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m1.1.1.cmml">σ</mi><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m1.1b"><ci id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m1.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m1.1.1">𝜎</ci></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m1.1c">italic-sigma</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m1.1d">\sigma</annotation></semantics></math> uncertainty in the number of publications
<math id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m2.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="N" display="inline"><semantics id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m2.1a"><mi id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m2.1.1" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m2.1.1.cmml">N</mi><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m2.1b"><ci id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m2.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m2.1.1">𝑁</ci></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m2.1c">italic-N</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m2.1d">N</annotation></semantics></math> is simply the <math id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\sqrt{N}" display="inline"><semantics id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1a"><msqrt id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1.cmml"><mi id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1.2" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1.2.cmml">N</mi></msqrt><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1b"><apply id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1"><root id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1a.cmml" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1"></root><ci id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1.2.cmml" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1.1.2">𝑁</ci></apply></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1c">italic-square-root ARG:start italic-N ARG:end</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m3.1d">\sqrt{N}</annotation></semantics></math>, then the 1<math id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m4.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\sigma" display="inline"><semantics id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m4.1a"><mi id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m4.1.1" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m4.1.1.cmml">σ</mi><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m4.1b"><ci id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m4.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m4.1.1">𝜎</ci></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m4.1c">italic-sigma</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m4.1d">\sigma</annotation></semantics></math> error on the 0.26 ratio of
WIYN to 4-m publications is 0.13. What does it mean for there to be a
“significant” enhancement in the scientific throughput? Boroson et al. (1998)
discuss how their simulation predicts this will depend upon program type,
TAC grade, and so on, and that overall about 2.5 times as many programs will be completed by queue observing than with classical observing. We take here
a more conservative approach: certainly a 50% increase (a factor of 1.5)
would be cause for celebration. Were this enhancement present, we would expect
there to be 1.5 <math id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m5.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\times" display="inline"><semantics id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m5.1a"><mo id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m5.1.1" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m5.1.1.cmml">×</mo><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m5.1b"><times id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m5.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m5.1.1"></times></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m5.1c">MULOP:times</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m5.1d">\times</annotation></semantics></math> 39.6% = 59.4% as many WIYN queue papers as 4-m
papers. We observe 0.26<math id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m6.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\pm" display="inline"><semantics id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m6.1a"><mo id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m6.1.1" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m6.1.1.cmml">±</mo><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m6.1b"><csymbol cd="latexml" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m6.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m6.1.1">plus-or-minus</csymbol></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m6.1c">ADDOP:plus-or-minus</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m6.1d">\pm</annotation></semantics></math>0.13
We thus can reject such an increase at a +2.5<math id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m7.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\sigma" display="inline"><semantics id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m7.1a"><mi id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m7.1.1" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m7.1.1.cmml">σ</mi><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m7.1b"><ci id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m7.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.SS1.p3.1.m7.1.1">𝜎</ci></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m7.1c">italic-sigma</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.SS1.p3.1.m7.1d">\sigma</annotation></semantics></math> level; i.e., with a 99.3%
confidence.<span id="footnote1" class="ltx_note ltx_role_footnote"><sup class="ltx_note_mark">1</sup><span class="ltx_note_outer"><span class="ltx_note_content"><sup class="ltx_note_mark">1</sup><span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_note">1</span>The rejection probability corresponding to +2.5<math id="footnote1.m1.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\sigma" display="inline"><semantics id="footnote1.m1.1b"><mi id="footnote1.m1.1.1" xref="footnote1.m1.1.1.cmml">σ</mi><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="footnote1.m1.1c"><ci id="footnote1.m1.1.1.cmml" xref="footnote1.m1.1.1">𝜎</ci></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="footnote1.m1.1d">italic-sigma</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="footnote1.m1.1e">\sigma</annotation></semantics></math>
was found by 
<span id="S3.Ex1" class="ltx_equation ltx_eqn_table">

<span class="ltx_equation ltx_eqn_row ltx_align_baseline">
<span class="ltx_eqn_cell ltx_eqn_center_padleft"></span>
<span class="ltx_eqn_cell ltx_align_center"><math id="S3.Ex1.m1.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="1.0-0.5\times(1.0-A_{G}(\mid x-\mu\mid/\sigma))," display="block"><semantics id="S3.Ex1.m1.1b"><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.cmml"><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.cmml"><mn id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.3" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.3.cmml">1.0</mn><mo id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.4" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.4.cmml">-</mo><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.cmml"><mn id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.7" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.7.cmml">0.5</mn><mo id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.8" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.8.cmml">×</mo><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.cmml"><mo stretchy="false" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.9" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.cmml">(</mo><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.cmml"><mn id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.12" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.12.cmml">1.0</mn><mo id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.13" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.13.cmml">-</mo><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.cmml"><msub id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.2" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.2.cmml"><mi id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.14" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.14.cmml">A</mi><mi id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.15.1" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.15.1.cmml">G</mi></msub><mo id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.1" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.1.cmml">⁢</mo><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.cmml"><mo stretchy="false" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.16" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.cmml">(</mo><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.cmml"><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1.1.cmml"><mo id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.17" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1.1.1.cmml">∣</mo><mrow id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1.2" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1.2.cmml"><mi id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.18" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.18.cmml">x</mi><mo id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.19" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.19.cmml">-</mo><mi id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.20" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.20.cmml">μ</mi></mrow><mo id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.21" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1.1.1.cmml">∣</mo></mrow><mo id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.22" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.22.cmml">/</mo><mi id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.23" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.23.cmml">σ</mi></mrow><mo stretchy="false" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.24" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.cmml">)</mo></mrow></mrow></mrow><mo stretchy="false" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.25" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.cmml">)</mo></mrow></mrow></mrow><mo id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.26" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.cmml">,</mo></mrow><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1c"><apply id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27"><minus id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.4.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.4"></minus><cn type="float" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.3.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.3">1.0</cn><apply id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1"><times id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.8.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.8"></times><cn type="float" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.7.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.7">0.5</cn><apply id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1"><minus id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.13.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.13"></minus><cn type="float" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.12.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.12">1.0</cn><apply id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1"><times id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.1"></times><apply id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.2.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.2"><csymbol cd="ambiguous" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.2.1.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.2">subscript</csymbol><ci id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.14.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.14">𝐴</ci><ci id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.15.1.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.15.1">𝐺</ci></apply><apply id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3"><divide id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.22.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.22"></divide><apply id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1"><csymbol cd="latexml" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.17">delimited-∣∣</csymbol><apply id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1.2.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.27.2.1.1.2.1.3.2.1.2"><minus id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.19.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.19"></minus><ci id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.18.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.18">𝑥</ci><ci id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.20.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.20">𝜇</ci></apply></apply><ci id="S3.Ex1.m1.1.23.cmml" xref="S3.Ex1.m1.1.23">𝜎</ci></apply></apply></apply></apply></apply></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1d">NUMBER:1.0 ADDOP:minus NUMBER:0.5 MULOP:times OPEN:( NUMBER:1.0 ADDOP:minus italic-A POSTSUBSCRIPT:start italic-G POSTSUBSCRIPT:end OPEN:( VERTBAR:mid italic-x ADDOP:minus italic-mu VERTBAR:mid MULOP:divide italic-sigma CLOSE:) CLOSE:) PUNCT:,</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.Ex1.m1.1e">1.0-0.5\times(1.0-A_{G}(\mid x-\mu\mid/\sigma)),</annotation></semantics></math></span>
<span class="ltx_eqn_cell ltx_eqn_center_padright"></span></span>
</span> where
<math id="footnote1.m2.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="A_{G}" display="inline"><semantics id="footnote1.m2.1b"><msub id="footnote1.m2.1.3" xref="footnote1.m2.1.3.cmml"><mi id="footnote1.m2.1.1" xref="footnote1.m2.1.1.cmml">A</mi><mi id="footnote1.m2.1.2.1" xref="footnote1.m2.1.2.1.cmml">G</mi></msub><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="footnote1.m2.1c"><apply id="footnote1.m2.1.3.cmml" xref="footnote1.m2.1.3"><csymbol cd="ambiguous" id="footnote1.m2.1.3.1.cmml" xref="footnote1.m2.1.3">subscript</csymbol><ci id="footnote1.m2.1.1.cmml" xref="footnote1.m2.1.1">𝐴</ci><ci id="footnote1.m2.1.2.1.cmml" xref="footnote1.m2.1.2.1">𝐺</ci></apply></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="footnote1.m2.1d">italic-A POSTSUBSCRIPT:start italic-G POSTSUBSCRIPT:end</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="footnote1.m2.1e">A_{G}</annotation></semantics></math> is the
integral probability of the normal distribution with a mean of <math id="footnote1.m3.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\mu" display="inline"><semantics id="footnote1.m3.1b"><mi id="footnote1.m3.1.1" xref="footnote1.m3.1.1.cmml">μ</mi><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="footnote1.m3.1c"><ci id="footnote1.m3.1.1.cmml" xref="footnote1.m3.1.1">𝜇</ci></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="footnote1.m3.1d">italic-mu</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="footnote1.m3.1e">\mu</annotation></semantics></math> and
a standard deviation of <math id="footnote1.m4.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\sigma" display="inline"><semantics id="footnote1.m4.1b"><mi id="footnote1.m4.1.1" xref="footnote1.m4.1.1.cmml">σ</mi><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="footnote1.m4.1c"><ci id="footnote1.m4.1.1.cmml" xref="footnote1.m4.1.1">𝜎</ci></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="footnote1.m4.1d">italic-sigma</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="footnote1.m4.1e">\sigma</annotation></semantics></math>; see, for example, Fig. C-2
in Bevington (1969).</span></span></span></p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="S3.SS2" class="ltx_subsection">
<h3 class="ltx_title ltx_title_subsection">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_subsection">3.2 </span>Comparison of Queue vs. Non-Queue Time at WIYN</h3>

<div id="S3.SS2.p1" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S3.SS2.p1.1" class="ltx_p">Of the 731 nights scheduled for science at WIYN during 1996B through 1998B,
we find that 260 nights were scheduled for queue observations (35.6%),
27 nights were scheduled for NOAO classical observations (3.7%), and 444 as
university time (60.7%). If queue observing produced
a significantly higher scientific throughput, we would expect significantly
more than 36% of the papers produced by WIYN data to be based on data obtained
with the queue. Instead, of the 28 total WIYN
papers in our sample, 9
(32%) were produced from queue data. This is
essentially
the same fraction of time on WIYN used by the queue (36%), and therefore does
not suggest that queue provides a significant advantage.</p>
</div>
<div id="S3.SS2.p2" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S3.SS2.p2.1" class="ltx_p">While the data fail to offer any support for the hypothesis, at what level
can we reject the claim, given our limited statistics? Using the same argument
as above that we would hope for a factor of 1.5 enhancement over the non-queue
publication rate, we can ask at what level can we exclude the queue publications
amounting to 1.5<math id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m1.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\times" display="inline"><semantics id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m1.1a"><mo id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m1.1.1" xref="S3.SS2.p2.1.m1.1.1.cmml">×</mo><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m1.1b"><times id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m1.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.SS2.p2.1.m1.1.1"></times></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m1.1c">MULOP:times</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m1.1d">\times</annotation></semantics></math> 35.6% = 53.4% of the total. The uncertainty
in our ratio 0.32 ratio is 0.17. Thus we can exclude a 50% enhancement at
the +1.3<math id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m2.1" class="ltx_Math" alttext="\sigma" display="inline"><semantics id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m2.1a"><mi id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m2.1.1" xref="S3.SS2.p2.1.m2.1.1.cmml">σ</mi><annotation-xml encoding="MathML-Content" id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m2.1b"><ci id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m2.1.1.cmml" xref="S3.SS2.p2.1.m2.1.1">𝜎</ci></annotation-xml><annotation encoding="application/x-llamapun" id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m2.1c">italic-sigma</annotation><annotation encoding="application/x-tex" id="S3.SS2.p2.1.m2.1d">\sigma</annotation></semantics></math> level; i.e., with an 89.8% confidence.</p>
</div>
<div id="S3.SS2.p3" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S3.SS2.p3.1" class="ltx_p">Nevertheless, it is clear that queue observing does
fare better in this comparison than it did in comparison to the 4-m control,
although still failing to produce a higher number of publications.
Several explanations
come to mind.
One possibility is that the 4-m simply operates more efficiently
than WIYN (at least in the time period when most of the data were acquired),
and that
it was thus easier to obtain usable data at the 4-m.
It is possible that review of queue proposals by an
outside TAC leads to a higher publication rate than time used by the
universities, who have a preallocated amount of time, which is divided up
internally. (As suggested earlier, the university time may be spent on
longer-term programs than the NOAO portion.) Finally, the 4-m supports a wider
complement of instrumentation (such as infrared imaging and spectroscopy) than WIYN,
which plausibly provides greater coverage of astronomical disciplines and
thus involvement in a wider variety of publications.</p>
</div>
<div id="S3.SS2.p4" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S3.SS2.p4.1" class="ltx_p">Although the numbers are small, the very high publication rate
for NOAO time that is scheduled <span id="S3.SS2.p4.1.1" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">classically</span> at WIYN suggests that it
may be the TAC process rather than the telescope or instrumentation
which explains why the queue
does better in this comparison than it does in comparison to the 4-m:
14% of the WIYN papers were produced by the small
(3.7%) time allocated to non-university classical observing.
The classically scheduled NOAO time
undergoes the same rigorous review as the queue
proposals, and thus is under the same pressure to publish rapidly.</p>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="S4" class="ltx_section">
<h2 class="ltx_title ltx_title_section">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_section">4 </span>Discussion</h2>

<div id="S4.p1" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S4.p1.1" class="ltx_p">Arguably, the WIYN queue has been as well run as it is possible for
any queue to be. A survey carried out of astronomers who had proposed for
queue time suggests that people were very satisfied with the quality of the
data they received (Boroson et al. 1998); some might expect that maintaining
data quality to be the hardest part of a queue.
Yet the evidence so far fails to support the suggestion that queue
observing leads to a higher scientific throughput, at least as measured by the
number of publications. Why does this differ from the dramatic predictions of simulations that suggest that a much higher percentage of programs should be
completed by the queue mode?</p>
</div>
<div id="S4.p2" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S4.p2.1" class="ltx_p">We have read through the papers based upon the WIYN queue data and have several observations of our own to offer. First, let us consider the advantage that
queue offers in providing easy “target of opportunity” (TOO) observations.
Of the full set of 11 papers (ignoring the 1996B cutoff), four rely on the
TOO advantage of queue for optical followup of
gamma-ray bursts (Galama et al. 1998) or supernovae
(Jha et al. 1999; Perlmutter et al. 1999; and Riess et al. 1998).
Although WIYN played a role in these important studies, our examination of
these papers suggests that it was a relatively minor role, with the
majority of the data coming from elsewhere. For instance,
there are considerably
more
data from the CTIO 4-m (which is classically scheduled) than from WIYN
in the Riess et al. (1998) study.
Inspection of these papers suggest that
there is no lack of ways for large groups to acquire such data.
The number of authors on these four papers range from
17 to 42, and with a large number of participants being a reflection of
the degree (and method?) of telescope access.
Thus TOO use of WIYN may not be more significant simply
because there
are other ways of obtaining such data.</p>
</div>
<div id="S4.p3" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S4.p3.1" class="ltx_p">One of the other purported advantages for queue observing is the ability to
take
advantage of particularly good
conditions, and indeed some programs may not be
completed any other way. However, this advantage is larger the greater the
range of conditions.
For instance, if the frequency histogram of delivered image quality (DIQ)
is very sharply peaked,
then queue offers less of an advantage, as all programs will obtain something
like the median seeing. At WIYN the median DIQ (at <span id="S4.p3.1.1" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">R</span>)
is
0.8 arcseconds, and 0.6 arcsecond or better images are achieved 18% of the
time (Green 1999).
Of the 11 queue papers listed in Table A1,
Armandroff, Jacoby, &amp; Davies (1999) is one of the clearest examples of taking
advantage of the queue to obtain the best DIQ.
The study utilized sub-arcsecond conditions (0.8 arcsec at <span id="S4.p3.1.2" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">B</span>,
0.6 arcsec at <span id="S4.p3.1.3" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">V</span>, and 0.7 arcsec at <span id="S4.p3.1.4" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">I</span>) for deep imaging of a newly
discovered dwarf member of the Local Group, Andromeda VI, after confirming its
nature using imaging at the 4-m. Nevertheless, these DIQ
values are not all that
different than the median values.</p>
</div>
<div id="S4.p4" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S4.p4.1" class="ltx_p">However, it may be that the sociological issues raised in the introduction dominate. The
use of queue may reduce the sense of “data ownership,” and given
situations of “data saturation,” we are more likely to publish the
data more rapidly if we have acquired them ourselves.
The use of “queue mode” on <span id="S4.p4.1.1" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">HST</span> has been perceived as being highly
successful,
although a meaningful control sample is hard to find for comparison; however,
one important difference comes to mind, namely that observing time (to US
proposers) usually comes with grants, providing a financial incentive to produce
results rapidly, coupled with a 1-year proprietary
period for unique data. An additional consideration is that <span id="S4.p4.1.2" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">HST</span> supplies
the user with fully reduced data, unlike WIYN, which provides basic calibration
data and requested standard observations, but which does not attempt a
“pipe-line” reduction. However, our own experience with <span id="S4.p4.1.3" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">HST</span> data is
that customized reductions are often needed in order to provide the data most
meaningful for a particular application.</p>
</div>
<div id="S4.p5" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S4.p5.1" class="ltx_p">Finally, it may be that we simply have not been sufficiently patient. As is evident from the 4-m publications, only one-third of the 4-m papers in
the past two years relied purely on “new” data (i.e., all data obtained in
the past 3.5 years). While our control samples explicitly took this into account,
we are nevertheless comparing numbers that are on the
the tails of the distribution of how quickly data finds its way into the
literature. This may be particularly true if the datasets from the WIYN
queue were to be larger than that in the control samples, or if they
take longer to reduce.
Current plans call for discontinuing the WIYN queue at the
end of semester 2000A, but continuing to provide some synoptic and target of opportunity service observing beyond that. It will be interesting to
re-examine the literature five years from now
using data obtained in 1996B-2000A
as the selection criterion.</p>
</div>
<div id="S4.p6" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S4.p6.1" class="ltx_p">We note that the quantity we would most like to measure is “quality”, but
this is of course harder to do in an objective manner. Citation rates might
provide one means, but not enough time has past for these to be meaningful.
Counting the number of papers is some measure of the “output” of a telescope,
but it is not necessarily the best; it does have the advantage of being
objective and reproducible, qualities usually assumed to be desirable
in any experiment.</p>
</div>
<div id="S4.p7" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S4.p7.1" class="ltx_p">Nevertheless, our results suggest that it
may benefit observatories to evaluate
their queue programs using some external measure, such as the number of
publications, if suitable controls can be defined.</p>
</div>
<div class="ltx_acknowledgements">Helmut Abt,
Dave De Young, David Sawyer,
Dave Silva, and Sidney C. Wolff were kind enough to
provide thoughtful comments
on the manuscript. We also benefited conversations with Taft Armandroff,
Bruce Bohannan, and
Abi Saha on the issues of queue observing.

</div>
</section>
<section id="S5" class="ltx_section">
<h2 class="ltx_title ltx_title_section">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_tag_section">5 </span>Appendix</h2>

<div id="S5.p1" class="ltx_para">
<p id="S5.p1.1" class="ltx_p">In Table A1 we present the list of papers published in the
<span id="S5.p1.1.1" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">Astronomical Journal</span>, the <span id="S5.p1.1.2" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">Astrophysical Journal</span> (Parts 1 and 2),
and the <span id="S5.p1.1.3" class="ltx_text ltx_font_italic">Publications of the Astronomical Society of the Pacific</span>
during 1998 and 1999 that used data from the 4-m and/or WIYN. We list
the dates of the first data obtained (from the relevant telescope). Often
this information was directly obtained from the paper, but in many cases we
had to contact the authors, or inspect the observing schedule or list of
queue programs to determine the actual data or semester.</p>
</div>
<section id="bib" class="ltx_bibliography">
<h2 class="ltx_title ltx_title_bibliography">References</h2>

<ul class="ltx_biblist">
<li id="bib.bib1" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(1)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Armandroff, T. E., Jacoby, G. H., &amp; Davies, J. E. 1999, AJ, 118,
1220

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib2" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(2)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib3" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(3)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Bevington, P. R. 1969, Data Reduction and Error Analysis for
the Physical Sciences (New York, McGraw-Hill)

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib4" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(4)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib5" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(5)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Bohannan, B. 1998, SPIE, 3349, 30.

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib6" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(6)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib7" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(7)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Boroson, T. 1996, in New Observing Modes for the
Next Century, ed. T. Boroson, J. Davies, &amp; I. Robson (San Francisco: ASP), 13

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib8" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(8)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib9" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(9)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Boroson, T., Harmer, D. L., Saha, A., Smith, P. S., Willmarth, D. W., &amp; Silva, D. R. 1998, SPIE, 3349, 41

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib10" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(10)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib11" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(11)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Galama, T. J. et al. (16 additional authors) 1998, ApJ, 497, L13

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib12" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(12)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib13" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(13)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Green, R. 1999 NOAO Newsletter No. 60, 38

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib14" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(14)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib15" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(15)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Jha, S. et al. (41 additional authors) 1999, ApJS, 125, 73

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib16" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(16)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib17" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(17)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Mountain, M. 1996, in New Observing Modes for the
Next Century, ed. T. Boroson, J. Davies, &amp; I. Robson (San Francisco: ASP), 235

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib18" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(18)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib19" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(19)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Perlmutter, S. et al. (31 additional authors) 1999, ApJ, 517, 565

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib20" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(20)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib21" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(21)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Riess, A. G. et al. (19 additional authors) 1998, AJ, 116, 1009

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib22" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(22)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib23" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(23)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock"> Silva, D., &amp; De Young, D. 1996, NOAO Newsletter 45, 36

</span>
</li>
<li id="bib.bib24" class="ltx_bibitem">
<span class="ltx_tag ltx_role_refnum ltx_tag_bibitem">(24)</span>
<span class="ltx_bibblock">
</span>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
</article>
</div>
<footer class="ltx_page_footer">
<div class="ltx_page_logo">Generated  on Wed Jul  3 21:37:27 2019 by <a href="http://dlmf.nist.gov/LaTeXML/">LaTeXML <img src="data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAAAsAAAAOCAYAAAD5YeaVAAAAAXNSR0IArs4c6QAAAAZiS0dEAP8A/wD/oL2nkwAAAAlwSFlzAAALEwAACxMBAJqcGAAAAAd0SU1FB9wKExQZLWTEaOUAAAAddEVYdENvbW1lbnQAQ3JlYXRlZCB3aXRoIFRoZSBHSU1Q72QlbgAAAdpJREFUKM9tkL+L2nAARz9fPZNCKFapUn8kyI0e4iRHSR1Kb8ng0lJw6FYHFwv2LwhOpcWxTjeUunYqOmqd6hEoRDhtDWdA8ApRYsSUCDHNt5ul13vz4w0vWCgUnnEc975arX6ORqN3VqtVZbfbTQC4uEHANM3jSqXymFI6yWazP2KxWAXAL9zCUa1Wy2tXVxheKA9YNoR8Pt+aTqe4FVVVvz05O6MBhqUIBGk8Hn8HAOVy+T+XLJfLS4ZhTiRJgqIoVBRFIoric47jPnmeB1mW/9rr9ZpSSn3Lsmir1fJZlqWlUonKsvwWwD8ymc/nXwVBeLjf7xEKhdBut9Hr9WgmkyGEkJwsy5eHG5vN5g0AKIoCAEgkEkin0wQAfN9/cXPdheu6P33fBwB4ngcAcByHJpPJl+fn54mD3Gg0NrquXxeLRQAAwzAYj8cwTZPwPH9/sVg8PXweDAauqqr2cDjEer1GJBLBZDJBs9mE4zjwfZ85lAGg2+06hmGgXq+j3+/DsixYlgVN03a9Xu8jgCNCyIegIAgx13Vfd7vdu+FweG8YRkjXdWy329+dTgeSJD3ieZ7RNO0VAXAPwDEAO5VKndi2fWrb9jWl9Esul6PZbDY9Go1OZ7PZ9z/lyuD3OozU2wAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==" alt="[LOGO]"></img>
</a>
</div></footer>
</div>
</body>
</html>
